This is the story of a conflict
of great violence
and whose end no one can foresee.
The story of a hatred
between two peoples
who have been fighting over the same land for decades.
Suicide attacks.
Air raids.
Urban guerrilla warfare.
Every day, the powder keg of the Middle East threatens peace.
This conflict, which no one understands anymore,
began a century ago.
This is the story
that we are going to tell you.
Why did some Jews decide to return to Israel?
the ancient kingdom of Judah,
After 2,000 years of exile?
Why did they fight against the British colonial troops?
How did they establish their dominance over the Palestinian Arabs?
Just a few years
after having undergone
One of the greatest traumas the world has ever known: Nazism.
For years,
Film enthusiasts
filmed their adventures.
Jews.
Arabs.
Their films
bear witness to the violence,
but also
of their daily lives,
of their hopes
and their dreams.
We found
these amateur films for you.
With Bärbel and Ella Weiler,
two little German Jewish girls
who narrowly escaped Nazi persecution along with
their parents.
With the Katz family,
These Eastern European Jews
who endured genocide
before secretly joining the State of Israel.
Along with the Arens,
Zionist activists.
We are going to tell you the story of the tragedy
and the odyssey of the Jewish people in the 20th century.
We will also be with the Saïd family.
Arabs
from Jerusalem.
With the Kouri
in the city of Jaffa,
as well as several actors
in the Palestinian drama.
We will follow them
in their revolt
and on the roads of exile.
From Hitler's rise to power in 1933
at the creation
of the State of Israel in 1948,
A look back at these 15 crucial years
that shaped the world
and which continue to this day
to weigh on its destiny.
Berlin.
It is April 1933.
Hitler has been in power for two months.
Germany's new leader
is an obsessive anti-Semite.
He accuses the Jews
of dominating and exploiting the world.
He declares
to one of his deputies:
"The economy is entirely
dominated by the Jews."
"It's their universal empire,"
"which they extended
over all the kingdoms."
"The struggle begins
between them and us."
"The stakes are
quite simply the fate of the world."
One month later,
Hitler attacked writers.
He organizes
nighttime ceremonies
where books written by communists are burned
and the Jews.
Hitler told the official
propaganda, Joseph Goebbels,
the task of converting
the German people to his theories.
German men and women,
The era of the absolute reign of Jewish intellectuals is drawing to a close.
The success of the German revolution
made it possible to liberate the country.
This is the time
of the German man.
Ten years earlier,
So, as a simple far-right activist,
Goebbels wrote in his diary:
"I hate the Jew
by instinct and by reason."
"He's poisoning us."
"He is odious and repugnant to me,"
"From the very depths of my soul."
At the same time
in the vicinity of Berlin.
These are the Weilers,
a small German Jewish family.
on holiday
by the lakes.
They are
Hitler's enemies.
The father, Friedrich,
is holding the camera.
He films his wife Hilse
and the two little girls they had together, Ella and Bärbel.
He is passionate about images.
He gave his daughters
a camera
so that they can immortalize
family happiness.
In their country house,
Bärbel and Ella
live a cloudless childhood
like all
little German girls their age.
This is paradise.
We're all in this together.
My mom is the best mom in the world.
And my father,
he's the strongest.
He is a former soldier.
He received the Iron Cross
during the First World War,
But lately,
he has been saying that he wants to leave Germany.
From the window
of the family apartment,
Little Ella recently
attended a Nazi parade.
I'm afraid of the soldiers
marching in the street.
Dad explained to me
that they were dangerous.
They sing,
they march in step in black boots.
Just seeing them is horrible.
The Weilers are very integrated into German society.
Little Ella goes to public school,
but she is the only Jewish girl in her class
And since the Nazis came to power,
she feels increasingly isolated.
The other children come up to me and say: Jew!
My teacher likes Nazis.
He explained to my father
that Jews are not allowed
to get very good grades.
I don't want to go to class anymore.
Designated
as public enemies,
However, there are very few Jews in Germany.
Less than 1%
of the population.
in France as well,
where, despite the far right,
one of them, Léon Blum,
is preparing to form
a left-wing government,
the Popular Front.
In Western Europe,
Most Jews are
perfectly integrated.
They obtained equal rights with other citizens in the 19th century.
Some of them,
like Sigmund Freud,
the inventor of psychoanalysis
or the physicist Albert Einstein,
They are among the great figures
of Western culture.
Of the 11 million
Jews in Europe,
Most of them are elsewhere.
They are in the East.
Look at
this exceptional document,
filmed at the time
of Hitler's rise to power.
This world
has completely disappeared.
We are in Munkacs
in Czechoslovakia.
Here, Jews represent
almost half of the population.
They live in a community.
By doing odd jobs
and in the worship
of their thousand-year-old tradition.
Some of them,
Religious Jews dress in clothing inherited from the 18th century.
They have
their own language: Yiddish.
And 3,000 years after Moses, they continue
to recite the prayers of the Hebrews.
Communities outside of time,
far from the world's major upheavals
and at the center of which
is the rabbi.
Here,
wearing a fur hat.
Continue to observe Shabbat
Listen to me,
respect the Shabbat and everything will be fine.
Say the prayers
We can't do less,
it's important
In 1933,
The Jews of Munkacs are far from imagining that in barely 15 years,
their community
will have been almost entirely exterminated.
Yet for centuries
Jews have lived in fear.
Traditionally in Europe,
They are held responsible for all the misfortunes that befall the population.
They are accused
of living off the work of others.
To be parasites.
And to belong
to an impure race.
Above all, Christians hold them responsible for the death of Christ.
2,000 years ago.
Absurd accusations
but ones that fuel hatred
and provoke
outbreaks of violence.
Massacres
that are called pogroms,
"Thunder"
in Russian.
The last wave of pogroms dates back to the end of the First World War.
when thousands
of Ukrainian nationalists
rushed
to attack the Jewish quarters
and massacred
tens of thousands of people.
An investigator,
Leo Motzkin, gives his testimony.
Old people and children
were cut into pieces.
Thousands
of women have been raped.
The victims were mutilated
in the most atrocious way.
They would cut off their right arm
and their left leg, or vice versa.
Here, the moral state of the Jewish population
is approaching madness.
In Eastern Europe,
more and more Jewish families
are now considering
going abroad.
This is the case in Kaunas,
in Lithuania, from the Katz family.
Shopkeepers who are also very integrated into the local community
They too are part of the local community
and established in the country
for about fifty years.
This home movie dates from 1929,
before Hitler came to power.
Here are the grandparents,
Vasya and her husband Zemar.
They are strolling
along the boulevards with their grandson.
Zvi,
aged three years.
Deloliah and Yitzhak,
parents,
All we have left is
this beautiful photograph
of the year
of their wedding.
Their eldest daughter is 16 years old.
Her name is Dita.
She is increasingly perceiving
anxiety within her own family.
I've heard about the pogroms in Poland and Ukraine.
My father recently said to my grandfather:
"Take our money"
"and take the whole family far away from here"
"because the Lithuanians will soon
throw the children out of the windows."
We are advised to leave.
But,
I don't want to.
Everyone here loves me.
And life is so beautiful for me.
200 kilometers away,
the same year.
We are in Riga,
the capital of Latvia.
This is the Arens family,
bourgeois Jews
like the Katz.
They own
a small confectionery factory.
They also film family members at their place.
with one of the very first
personal cameras.
Same fake smiles,
same apparent good humor.
However,
among the Arens,
Some have already made the decision to leave the country.
This is the case of this 16-year-old boy,
who teases his cousins ​​in front of the camera.
His name is Mickaël.
As
this photo shows,
Mickaël Arens,
here, in uniform,
belongs
to a youth organization.
He is one of those Jewish activists
which we see
more and more in Eastern Europe
in the village squares.
They are called
the Zionists.
They adopted an anthem,
the HaTikvah.
Which means
hope in Hebrew.
Their hope is to reach Palestine.
on the other side
of the Mediterranean
and to settle here,
on the hill of Zion,
in Jerusalem,
the ancient capital of the Jews.
Zionism was born
in the 19th century,
long before Hitler.
For the founder
of the movement, Theodor Herzl,
The Jews will always be threatened.
wherever they may be.
Whether they integrate into society
or live as a minority
according to their tradition.
They must therefore
form a nation
and found
their own homeland
where they can
defend themselves.
Physical training,
Hebrew lessons,
before their departure
for the land of their ancestors,
Thousands of young Jews
are taken in hand and trained.
They learn agriculture
on Zionist farms.
These are they,
the future pioneers of Israel.
In the early
1930s,
This is one of those farms
that Mickaël and his group are visiting.
Betar,
a radical Zionist movement.
We're going to sleep
in a tent.
We sing.
We're training.
For us,
it is a necessity to fight
because we all share
a love for Palestine.
This land
which is part of our history.
In the 1930s,
These are the great powers
that divide up the Middle East.
After
World War I,
France was entrusted with
control of Lebanon and Syria.
Already present in Egypt,
Great Britain administers
Transjordan and Palestine.
In 1917,
with the Balfour Declaration,
Great Britain officially opens
the doors of Palestine to the Jews.
Every year,
Thousands of them arrive
in the promised land with their families
and a few belongings
that they were able to take with them.
They join
a small local community
who has never
left the region
and who has never ceased to pray here,
before the Wailing Wall.
This is the cradle of Judaism.
The last remaining vestige of the temple
built 2,000 years ago by Herod,
the king of the Jews.
The temple
was destroyed by the Romans.
Today, only the perimeter walls remain.
A few meters
above the wall,
Muslims built one of their most beautiful religious buildings.
According to the Quran,
The Prophet Muhammad gained paradise
here in the 7th century AD.
It was also in Jerusalem
that Christianity was born.
Every year,
Thousands of people
go on pilgrimage
at the site
of Jesus' death.
It is on this thrice-holy land
that the Zionists intend to
implement their project.
To found
their new homeland
and establish themselves
permanently.
Everywhere
in Palestine,
They are founding
a new type of agricultural village,
the kibbutzim.
In one of them
is a young Polish Jew,
Joel Iglinskiy.
I had
no future in Poland.
Here, we're one big family.
We're going back to agriculture,
like in the Bible.
Men and women,
we work all day
while
our children are at daycare.
In the kibbutz,
we are all equal,
We share everything.
Each person pays their salary to the community.
and we make
all our decisions together.
For these idealistic young people
who came from the far reaches of Europe,
The experience is unique.
With his classmates,
Joël Iglinskiy simply intends to
build a different world.
We have committed ourselves
to building socialism.
The red flag
flies over the kibbutz.
We admire Herzl,
Léon Blum and Marx.
We are revolutionaries.
And we know
that we're going to change the world.
On site,
The inhabitants who witnessed the arrival of the Jews wondered what was happening.
What do the Zionists want?
How far will the colonization of land go?
Why
do they come to Palestine?
In the 1930s,
The Arabs of Palestine
number one million.
They represent
two-thirds of the population
and are distributed
throughout the territory
in hundreds
of towns and villages.
They are called
the Palestinians
in memory of the Philistine people of antiquity.
Before the arrival of the British,
they lived under the Turkish empire.
for four centuries.
Look at these color images
shot at the beginning of the 20th century.
Their Eastern culture
has always fascinated visitors.
Some of them are Bedouins.
They live in the desert
with their herds,
but most of them
are farmers.
They work
for large Arab landowners,
like here,
on the coastal plain,
where the famous Jaffa oranges are produced.
They are exported
all over the world.
For several years now,
Some Arab landowners agree
to sell their land to the Zionists.
And little by little,
the face of Palestine is changing.
By 1935, Jews already represented 30% of the population.
They created dozens of villages along the coast and to the north.
This does not prevent
most Arab families
to live
the pre-war years without suspicion
and in
a certain happiness.
This is the case,
in Jerusalem, of the Said family.
Christian Arabs,
who own a publishing house.
Filmed by his father
during the summer holidays,
This boy's name is Edward.
This is the future
Palestinian writer Edward Said.
Our family home
was located in Talbiya,
a neighborhood
of Christian Palestinians like us.
The imposing two-story villa
had many bedrooms
and a lovely garden in which
my two youngest cousins,
My sisters and I could play.
It was
an idyllic time.
In their family film,
nothing yet suggests
that this idyllic period
is about to end.
At the same time,
in Germany.
The situation is becoming
dramatic for the Jews.
The Nazis who sought
to create an ethnically pure country,
multiply
the provocations
and anti-Semitic graffiti is spreading throughout the country.
On the trams
and even
on public benches.
At the congress
of Nuremberg in 1935,
The Nazis officially excluded
Jews from the national community.
Among German Jews,
panic is beginning to set in.
And more and more people are seeking to flee abroad.
to France,
Great Britain or the United States.
This is where a Jewish community of 4 million people already lives.
But visas for Western countries
are granted sparingly.
Thus, more than 100,000 German Jews
chose Palestine
where the doors of immigration
are still open to them.
Around one hundred Jewish families
arrive in Palestine
aboard the Mariette Pacha,
of the Compagnie des Messageries Maritimes.
Most of them
are in a state of absolute destitution,
Reich laws prohibiting
Jews from transferring their property.
Zionist associations
are welcoming these unfortunate people
and give them
the means to rebuild their lives.
Among the passengers
of the Mariette Pacha were the Weilers,
our Jewish family from Berlin.
Unlike the other passengers,
the Weilers are simply visitors.
Without yet knowing
if they will settle in Palestine
with their two little girls
and leave Germany for good.
They continue filming
with their personal camera.
To convince his wife,
Friedrich Weiler took her on a tour of the country.
He takes her
to the shores of the Dead Sea.
They are visiting Tel Aviv,
this Jewish metropolis of 130,000 inhabitants
built from the ground
in less than 20 years.
They are visiting German friends who have already settled there.
Yet,
After a week of travel,
they are still hesitant to take the plunge.
In Jerusalem,
They found
a city in turmoil,
close to revolt.
At the call of the Grand Mufti,
Palestinian Arabs demonstrate against the British occupation.
and its favorable policy
to the mass arrival of Jews.
One of their spokespeople explains.
Since the beginning of the 1930s,
Demonstrations
continue in Palestine.
Increasingly violent.
Attacks
against the kibbutzim,
attacks
in the middle of the street.
In 1936, what is known as
the great Arab revolt finally broke out.
One of its leaders
is named Fawzi al-Qawuqji.
He launches a guerrilla war
against the British army.
We are rebelling
against injustices,
against Zionism,
to defend
our Holy Land.
The English
abused Arab blood.
Today,
we are ready to face them.
The revolt spreads
within a few months to all of Palestine
and it forces
the British to send reinforcements.
The repression is relentless.
As here in Jaffa, where a neighborhood
is emptied of its inhabitants and razed.
It took the British army two years
to quell the revolt,
but this is
only temporary.
In 1938,
on one of the Arab peasants taken prisoner,
We find a leaflet;
it sounds like a warning.
Today, you are cruelly trying
to strip us of our rights,
from our homes,
of our honor.
Know that never,
before we have won our freedom,
We will not surrender our weapons.
The same year,
in Germany.
It is
November 9, 1938.
In front of the public
who observe and sometimes approve,
The Nazis set fire to
Jewish places of worship.
It's Kristallnacht.
A massive pogrom during which
8,000 shops were looted
and about a hundred
Jews murdered.
A few months earlier,
Germany took control
of Austria, where 200,000 Jews lived.
In a new wave of antisemitism,
Tensions are rising sharply in Europe.
and the risk of a new world war is drawing closer.
Some European Jews
realize that for them,
The countdown has begun.
Shortly before Kristallnacht,
The Weilers have made the decision
to leave Berlin permanently
and to emigrate to Palestine.
In the photos taken before departure,
the parents are trying to put on a brave face,
But Friedrich notes in his diary:
"We are spending the last few days
in fear."
"Until the very end
I feared the Gestapo"
"requires
an additional formality from us."
"On the last night, my mother
felt like she was suffocating at the thought of our departure."
Friedrich's mother, Ida,
decided to stay in Germany.
She tries to reassure
her little girls.
The Nazis,
there's no need to worry.
We only have them for a while.
All of this, you'll see,
it will pass.
Berlin,
the day of departure.
The parents
take some final photos on the platform.
Grandmother Ida came to say goodbye to the whole family.
Ella, his little girl,
here on the right, is enthusiastic.
She doesn't realize that she is seeing her grandmother for the last time.
I'm excited about this trip.
It's a new life
that begins.
We are crossing Austria
where Hitler has just seized power.
We cross the Alps.
This is the first time
I've seen such large mountains.
And then, there we were,
we found ourselves in Italy.
The Nazis,
with their wickedness, are behind us.
The family embarked
for Palestine.
Our boat
is called the Jerusalem.
To pass the time,
Mom knits
And me,
I read books all day.
After five days at sea,
the Weilers landed in Palestine.
The parents chose to settle
in a small house north of Tel Aviv
where they believe their two daughters
will be able to grow up in safety.
They will soon learn
that they are among the last
to have been able to
reach Palestine.
Because in the spring of 1939,
The situation
changed abruptly.
Great Britain,
which still occupies Palestine,
makes a decision
that changes everything.
To secure the support of the Arabs
in the next war against Hitler,
The British decide
to cease supporting Zionism.
To limit the number
of entry visas for Jews
as well as land purchases.
A catastrophic decision for the Zionists.
who planned to force millions of Jews to emigrate from Europe
before the outbreak of war.
Their leader in Palestine,
David Ben-Gurion,
in turn, chose to force the issue.
He decides to accelerate
the tower and palisade operations,
these colony creations
which have multiplied in previous years
and which rely
on the element of surprise.
It is July 12, 1939,
in Negba, near the Negev desert.
Zionist militants
charged at a convoy
prefabricated houses
that they are going to install here.
On these lands
which they had previously bought from the Arabs.
Among them
is Joel Iglinskiy.
"We need to move quickly."
"Everyone knows what they have to do."
"We erect fences by putting
gravel inside the planks"
"To stop the bullets."
"We're going up
the watchtower."
"We forget about the fatigue"
"because we are
the soldiers of the Zionist revolution"
"And we know we're doing something bigger than ourselves."
In the summer of 1939,
as the impending cataclysm approached,
The Jews are holding their breath.
Some,
as we have shown,
sought refuge
by emigrating to Palestine.
Others still hope to continue
living in Europe despite the danger.
It will only take them a few months
to achieve the unimaginable.
The Nazis' plan to destroy
an entire people.
This is the new chapter
that we are now going to tell you about.
September 1, 1939,
Germany invaded Poland.
This is the beginning
of the Second World War.
From the very first weeks,
the Nazis, who crushed the Polish army,
they are increasing their abuses.
Forced labor
blows,
humiliations,
as dozens of photos taken across the country show,
German soldiers
unleashed their fury against the Jews.
Hitler ordered
the roundup of Polish Jews,
men, women, and children,
in quarters reserved for them,
the ghettos.
The Nazis chose to isolate
their future victims from the rest of the world,
to starve them little by little,
before, soon, deciding
to murder them en masse, here.
The massacre begins
a year and a half later,
June 22, 1941,
when the German army
attacked the USSR.
A lightning offensive which,
in just a few days,
pushes the Soviets back
for hundreds of kilometers.
In the conquered cities,
The Nazis immediately launched
the persecution of the Jews
by getting help
from the population.
Everywhere, like here in Zloczow,
pro-German nationalists
far-right activists
and convicted criminals
launch pogroms
under the encouragement of the Germans.
They accuse the Jews
of being responsible for massacres
which were committed by the Soviets
a few days earlier.
In Lviv, Ukraine,
A German soldier films the crowd
and the Ukrainian militiamen.
Dozens
of Jewish women,
After being raped,
they will be murdered along with their families.
An SS sergeant, Félix Landau,
who was nevertheless fiercely anti-Semitic,
is surprised
by this outburst of violence.
"We see things that are almost impossible to describe."
"Hundreds
of Jews covered in blood,"
"holes in the head,"
"broken hands"
"and the eyes dangling
out of their sockets"
"are being beaten up"
"of hatred"
"and rage."
Within hours, the massacre
spread to dozens of cities.
Still on July 4th,
The Germans are approaching Kaunas in Lithuania.
This is where Dita Katz and her entire family live.
Do you remember that film
shot twelve years earlier, in 1929?
When the Germans arrived, the grandfather
tried to reassure his family.
"Don't be afraid of the Germans."
"I knew them
during the First World War."
"They are civilized people."
However,
from the very first hours,
His own son, Itzhak,
disappears around a street corner.
The rest,
is told by a German corporal.
"Lithuanians
with sticks and crowbars,"
"strike
the Jews on the ground,"
"on the skull
or on the face."
"Indiscriminately,
they are beaten."
"until they show no further
signs of life."
"In three-quarters of an hour,"
"the one presented
as the city's executioner"
"killed
about fifty people."
"All around,
the Germans are watching the spectacle."
In Bavaria,
from his mountain chalet,
Hitler approves of the pogroms.
But he wants to supervise them.
and rationalize them.
He tasked Heinrich Himmler,
the head of the SS, seen here on the left,
to assemble special units:
the Einsatzgruppen.
Their mission is to eliminate
in a few months
any trace of the Jewish people
in the conquered territories.
The Einsatzgruppen will shoot the Jews directly into mass graves.
In Libau,
not far from Kaunas,
the soldier
of the German navy,
Reinhardt Wiener,
filmed one of these massacres with his personal camera.
A truck arrives.
The guards force
the Jews to jump to the ground.
Among them are
weak and sick men,
They help each other.
They are being pushed
towards the trench by an SS officer.
When they arrive
in the trench,
They must walk
over bodies covered in sand,
The firing squad
stands before them,
They are asked
to turn around
while waiting for the next group to arrive.
The scale of the massacre
is unparalleled in history.
In six months, the Einsatzgruppen
murdered half a million Jews.
In front of his troops,
Himmler gives the order.
"What should be done with the women and children?"
"I think we cannot
exterminate men"
"and at the same time
let their children grow up"
"so that they can take revenge later
on our children and grandchildren."
At the end of 1941,
Information about the genocide is starting to filter through.
In Palestine, the Arab population
remains uninvolved in the conflict.
Even though his spiritual leader,
the Grand Mufti of Jerusalem,
Exiled by the British,
chose to collaborate with Hitler.
He raised a regiment
of pro-Nazi Bosnian Muslims.
The Jews,
are alarmed
to no longer receive news from their loved ones.
This is the case of Mickaël Arens,
the young Zionist from Riga,
who arrived in Palestine in 1938
and who joined the police force.
He is unaware that his mother,
who remained in Latvia,
was killed in the first few days
of the German offensive.
Friedrich Weiler, too,
can no longer communicate with his mother.
Ida,
who stayed in Berlin.
On November 2, 1941,
he wrote in his diary.
"Horrible news
from Germany."
"The Jews who are there
are being deported from their homes."
"and sent
like cattle to Poland."
"These stories are so inhumane
that they are hard to believe."
"They are asked to dig
and they are massacred in these graves."
In November 1941,
Ida Weiler, the grandmother,
has already been deported to the east.
It is located here
in Lodz, Poland,
along with 140,000 other Jews.
All those
who escaped the first pogroms
are now
confined to the ghettos.
This is the case,
in Kaunas, of Dita Katz.
With his mother
and his little brother Zvi,
with her fiancé Yehuda,
Dita no longer harbors any illusions about her fate.
"I know
ever since my father disappeared"
"that the Nazis
are exterminating us."
"What's happening
is unimaginable"
"And nobody
is helping us."
At the end of 1941,
the Nazis, who occupy
almost all of Europe,
launch
the final solution.
This is
the second phase of the Holocaust.
From all over France
with the help of the Vichy regime.
In Romania,
in Yugoslavia,
in Poland,
The Jews are being gathered together
then directed
in a panic
to
unknown destinations.
This is from Holland,
at the Westerbork transit camp,
that we have the most accurate testimony of the deportation of the Jews.
These images were taken
by German soldiers.
These are unique documents.
Every morning, a train takes several thousand people eastward.
A Jewish nurse,
Etty Hillesum, is present at the departure.
"The livestock trucks
are gradually filling up."
"I see an elderly person being transported
in the final stages of the illness"
"And who says
the prayer for the dead."
"Babies with their piercing little cries
that were torn from their cradles."
"Young women
are already seated in the train car."
"Will these doors really close?"
"Alas, yes."
"The narrow openings
still allow glimpses of faces."
"Will we one day be able to describe to the outside world?"
"What happened here?"
So that the world may realize
the tragedy that has befallen the Jewish people,
We will have to wait
another two years.
Spring 1945,
the end
of the Second World War.
After five years
of nightmares,
Europe celebrates victory
against the Nazi regime.
One of the worst the world has ever known.
During the winter,
Allied and Soviet soldiers
liberated dozens of extermination and labor camps.
Majdanek,
Auschwitz,
Bergen-Belsen.
And the world learned
how the majority of the victims perished.
In gas chambers
and crematorium ovens
which sometimes still burn
when the camps are liberated.
The death toll is
5 million Jewish victims.
6 million,
we learn a little later.
How could the world have allowed this genocide to happen?
At a meeting
of the World Jewish Congress,
one of the leaders
of the Zionist movement,
Nahum Goldmann,
lets his anger explode.
The port of Haifa, in Palestine,
a few months after the end of the war.
On makeshift boats,
sometimes on the verge of sinking,
The first survivors of the camps
reach the Holy Land.
On one of these boats
is a Polish Jew,
Garcher Rabinovitch.
"From where I am,
Palestine appears to me as paradise."
"This is the first light
I've seen in 17 years."
"I'm crying tears of joy."
"You know what it's like
to be welcomed somewhere"
"after having been hated"
"and chased
from country to country?"
Relief for some,
but concern for others.
In the face of the arrival
of Jewish survivors from Europe,
Once again,
the Arabs of Palestine are protesting.
In Jaffa, a teenager,
Youssef Chaker, asks the question.
"The Jews suffered horribly
during World War II."
"But we Arabs,
we have nothing to do with it."
"Why we should
suffer the consequences"
"of the Nazi genocide
against the Jews?"
"Why don't they go and create their own state in Europe?"
"Where they were massacred,
instead of coming to our country?"
To deter
any further Arab revolt,
Great Britain continues
to implement its pre-war policy.
It forbade Jews
from going to Palestine,
But this time, she's having all undocumented immigrants arrested.
and groups them
into camps.
After the Nazi death camps,
Holocaust survivors are familiar with
British prisoner-of-war camps.
They will react soon.
In Europe, 150,000 Jewish survivors
are waiting near former Nazi camps,
like here,
in Austria.
They are hesitant
to return to Poland or Russia
where they fear encountering
the anti-Semitism they have always known.
Among them
is Dita Katz,
who miraculously
survived the death camps.
Despite the death of her father in 1941
and that of her husband in 1944,
Dita chooses to return
to her hometown.
In Lithuania, where she hopes to
reconnect with her pre-war friends
and rebuild his life.
His younger brother Zvi,
the boy filmed in 1929,
is now 18 years old.
He too survived the Holocaust,
but he made a different choice.
With his mother,
they decide to go to Palestine.
To circumvent
the British ban,
He made contact
with an underground network
And it is Zionist agents
who will make him travel all over Europe
without identity papers
and without a visa.
In 1947, one of these trips was filmed
by the American journalist Meyer Levin.
By train, then by truck,
Zvi and her mother travel across Poland,
Czechoslovakia,
Germany, Austria.
After several
weeks of travel,
They are dropped off at the foot of the Alps
with a group of refugees
And they will cross the Italian border illegally on foot.
"There are women and children with us."
"But nothing can stop us from joining Palestine."
"We are at an altitude of 2,700 meters,"
"Mom is not giving up."
"We feel
confident"
"because we know that we're finally going to
have a country, like everyone else."
On the other side of the border,
they embark in the Rome region
at night,
on a clandestine ship.
It is from here that dozens of ships
take Jews to Palestine
to land them
on a deserted beach.
High-risk travel.
One of these boats,
The Exodus was recently boarded
by the British fleet.
The boarding resulted in
several deaths and injuries
and the Exodus
was sent back to Germany.
This time, the Zionists
want to take every precaution.
As soon as a ship is sighted,
The 950 illegal passengers
are ordered to evacuate the bridge
and they take refuge
in the holds.
The journalist
Meyer Levin continues filming
while his partner,
Tereska Torrès, keeps a logbook.
"This boat is a raft
of the modern-day Medusa."
"There is almost no air, no light,
only an unbreathable smell."
"The women,
often hysterical, faint."
"Around 1 a.m.
a little boy was born."
"The mother screamed at the top of her lungs
for two hours."
After 12 days at sea,
as the ship nears its destination,
A plane
flies over the stowaways.
It is followed
by a British warship
who approaches
and orders the machines to stop.
Unmasked,
the passengers emerge into the daylight.
For them, as Tereska Torrès notes in her diary,
The dream ends when the English soldiers
take control of the ship.
"We are living through the final hours of the ship."
"As we approach Haifa,"
"The city rises
before us,"
"So beautiful and forbidden
to these poor people."
"A company of armed and helmeted soldiers is waiting for us on the platform."
The passengers are all being sent
to prison camps
that the British
established on the island of Cyprus.
They are there, locked up
behind new barbed wire,
that Zvi Katz and her mother
will spend several months.
For them and for Zionist activists,
the situation has become unbearable.
In Palestine, Jewish armed groups
decide to take action
and to launch
a campaign of terror.
Extremely violent attacks
which aim to force the British to back down
and drive them out of Palestine.
On the clandestine radio station,
an 18-year-old terrorist,
Gueoulah Cohen, threat.
"You British,"
"You will pay for
every tear of a Jew who holds out his hands."
"and to whom
you refuse help."
"Hell is about to enter your lives"
"and terror will flood
every part of your body."
"For we have sworn an oath
to liberate the land of Israel."
In Palestine, Arab attacks
are now a response to Jewish attacks.
And the region is once again
on the verge of explosion.
Then news arrived from New York that changed everything.
It is November 29, 1947,
at the United Nations headquarters.
An extraordinary general meeting is to be held that day.
One of those
that will make history.
Commission of inquiry,
public hearing
speech.
For the past year, the international community
has been studying a solution for the Middle East
and she is preparing to vote on the territorial partition of Palestine.
In green, the territories
offered to the Arabs,
In blue,
those that are offered to Jews.
In the middle,
the Jerusalem region,
which would be administered
by the international community.
The Zionists
accepted the partition,
But the Arab countries
all announced that they would vote against it.
To be adopted, the project must
receive two-thirds of the votes.
Consumed by guilt
towards the Jewish people,
The United States announced
that they would vote for
and Great Britain
that it would abstain.
The suspense
involves two countries.
Tempted to the very end
by abstention,
France has just given
a boost to the Zionists.
It is followed by the Soviet Union.
That's unexpected.
But the major powers
sway the vote.
In a few minutes,
the Zionist cause
has just progressed
like never before.
In the Tel Aviv crowd that erupted
with joy at the announcement of the news,
There is the young Berliner, Bärbel Weiler.
"Our dream is
becoming a reality."
"The Jewish state
is getting closer to us."
"It's fantastic."
"We dance,
we laugh, we sing."
"Everyone
kisses each other without knowing each other."
"What joy!"
They crossed the borders clandestinely.
They reached their promised land
on makeshift ships,
They now have the support of the international community.
At the end of 1947,
the Zionists seemed close to their goal.
Will the two peoples now be able to reach an agreement?
According to the UN,
The partition
must be followed by two separate states,
One was Jewish,
the other Arab.
We will explain to you
Why did this project collapse in just six months?
and how the creation of Israel plunged
the Arabs of Palestine into misfortune
and exile
for decades.
November 30, 1947,
the day after the UN vote.
A young Arab woman from Jaffa,
Afif Elkouri, is outraged.
"Why should we give away half the country?"
"So that they can make it
a Jewish state?"
"And what will become of the non-Jews?"
"Now,
there is only one solution left: to fight."
To defend their rights,
Thousands of peasants
join the guerrilla war.
One of their leaders
is Fawzi al-Qawuqji.
One of the heroes
of the great Arab revolt of 1936.
He only has a few weeks
to train his troops.
"My soldiers only have basic weapons
that they bought themselves."
"We sent SOS signals to neighboring Arab countries, but in vain."
"Yet, the hatred is so intense
that one is ready to sacrifice oneself."
In the opposing camp,
The Haganah, Israel's future army,
has been training for months.
Surrounded by World War II veterans,
It is made up of
highly motivated young recruits.
Among them, Zvi Katz,
here, on the right of the photo.
He escaped from the Cyprus camp
thanks to an underground network.
"I only think about fighting."
"For us,
it's a matter of dignity."
"We no longer want to be like
animals who are killed without saying a word."
"Never again will we allow ourselves to be slaughtered like sheep."
The two young Berliners,
Ella and Bärbel Weiler,
They, too,
joined the Haganah.
They have just learned
that their grandmother died
during the war in Poland,
murdered by the Nazis
They are determined.
"During the war,
no one acted to save the Jews."
"Today,
we can only rely on ourselves."
"If we don't help ourselves, who will help us?"
In the spring of 1948,
Fawzi al-Qawuqji
and other Arab leaders
launch their troops
to assault the Jewish positions.
One of the targets
is Kibbutz Mishmar Haemek,
the crossing point
from Galilee to Tel Aviv.
"We start at 5 a.m.,
on the Jewish Sabbath."
"I give the order
to fire the cannon"
"to destroy as many houses as possible."
"They seem to have suffered heavy losses."
Opposite them, the defenders of the kibbutz
respond blow for blow.
One of them,
Joël Lotan, is filming the fights.
"We are trying
to repel the enemy."
"And we hope to hold out
until reinforcements arrive."
"Fortunately,
after a few days,"
"Haganah soldiers eventually reached us from the hills,"
"From Haifa."
Within days,
Palestine was engulfed in flames.
Offensive,
counter-offensive,
the Haganah,
better organized than the Arab army,
manages to gain the upper hand
from the very first weeks
and to take
thousands of prisoners.
In the conquered cities,
the population is becoming frightened
and is considering
fleeing the fighting.
On April 9, 1948,
an event reinforced these fears.
In Deir Yassin, Jewish extremists massacred nearly 200 Arab villagers.
including children.
A massacre
of which no images remain,
but whose news
is spreading around the world
and triggers panic.
In Jaffa,
a few rare photos taken on the spot
show the residents
who are abandoning their homes
and leave the city.
Among them
is Youssef Chaker.
"We heard about Deir Yassin on the radio."
"We heard that the Arab countries
were going to come to our aid."
"In the meantime,
we prefer to leave."
"I get into a truck, we pile in
and we head towards Beirut."
This is the beginning
of the Palestinian exodus.
A few streets away
is Afif Elkouri.
"The whole city is
fleeing."
"On Arabic radio, they tell us
that we'll be back in two weeks,"
"But
is that really true?"
Those who fled will never be allowed to return home.
Now, the city of Jaffa,
deserted by its inhabitants,
will be officially considered
an Israeli city.
May 14, 1948,
the day everything changed.
It is 10 a.m.
at the port of Haifa.
British Governor Alan Cunningham
is embarking for England.
Britain ends three decades of presence in Palestine
and leaves
the two sides facing each other.
Six hours later, in Tel Aviv,
The leader of the Zionists, David Ben-Gurion,
decided to proclaim the Jewish state.
After
years of struggle,
The Zionists
are reconnecting with Jewish history.
Behind their flag will rally
a minority of Palestinian Arabs.
150,000 people
who choose to stay put
and who will become Israeli citizens.
Today,
60 years later, they represent 20% of the population.
But most
of the Palestinian Arabs take to the road.
It's almost
an entire people,
Men, women and children,
who are now fleeing abroad.
It is called the Nakba,
the catastrophe in Arabic.
The exodus that began in April
after the Deir Yassin massacre,
will affect
more than 700,000 people.
Two-thirds
of the Arab population.
Seven Arab countries declare war on Israel
the day after
Ben-Gurion's speech,
It changes nothing
about their fate.
After several weeks of battle and
the capture of the Old City of Jerusalem,
after several
spectacular advances,
The Arab armies are retreating
and losing more territory.
This situation further increases the flow of Palestinian refugees.
According to the latest historical research
conducted in Israel,
half
were allegedly forcibly expelled
by Israeli soldiers.
They found refuge
in neighboring Arab countries,
in Jordan or Lebanon,
in refugee camps.
Among them
is Abu Hicham, 19 years old.
"We were given tents."
"The ground is soaked."
"We no longer have a country."
"We can no longer
live normally."
"We are being given
bread and cheese."
"I feel humiliated
and I can only think of one thing,"
"to return to my village."
"For as long as it takes,
we will fight."
Hate,
humiliation,
exile.
In 1948,
the history
of the Israeli-Arab conflict
This is just the beginning.
Today, Abu Hicham, 78,
still has refugee status.
He lives in a Palestinian camp
in the suburbs of Beirut, Lebanon,
a few kilometers
from Afif Elkouri.
For 60 years,
Neither of them was allowed
to return to live in their native land,
Palestine.
Some emigrated to the West,
like Edward Said,
the little Arab Christian from Jerusalem.
He became a university professor
in New York,
Edward Said was one of the most famous spokespeople for the Palestinian people.
until his death in 2003.
On the other side, in Israel,
they all tried to rebuild their lives
despite the trauma
of the Second World War.
Mickaël Arens, the young Zionist from Riga,
dedicated himself to agriculture in Galilee.
Deeply affected
by her childhood memories,
Berliner Ella Weiler married
a Jewish man who, like her, came from Germany.
They had
two children.
His sister, Bärbel,
She married a Polish Auschwitz survivor.
She lives with him
in Tel Aviv.
Grateful to her father,
who died in the 1960s,
for having made him leave Germany
when there was still time.
It was only in 1972 that Dita Katz
left Lithuania for Israel.
There she was reunited with her brother Zvi,
who had become a reserve officer.
They live in Tel Aviv
in the memory of their loved ones
murdered by the Nazis.
Perhaps the most surprising is
Joel Iglinskiy.
At 99 years old,
he still lives in Nekbah,
the kibbutz
which he created in 1939.
More than ever, he remains faithful
to the socialist ideal of his youth.